Today's דף daf is נ"ו nun vav 56. We pick up at
the bottom of נ"ה nun heh עמוד ב' amud bet and we're
talking about what types of structures can be considered to be
part of the boundaries of the city to extend the boundaries of
the city for עירוב תחומין eruv techumin purposes. And the basic point
is something that is made for habitation and fit for habitation even
if it's not currently being inhabited as רש"י Rashi consistently reiterates. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר
רב הונא,
Amar
Rav Huna, it is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8,
9, 10, 11, 12 lines down in the wide lines, starts the
line starts with the word בניין גופה. binyan gufeh. And now we
do middle of the line, אמר רב הונא. Amar Rav Huna. So
says רב הונא, Rav Huna, יושבי צריפים אין מודדין להם אלא מפתח
בתיהם. yoshvei tzerifim ein modedin lahem ela mi-petach bateihem. Those that live
in like huts made out of
thatch, is that what it's called, thatch huts? Yeah, thatch huts, basically
you know they are not part of the city and even if
you have a whole city made out of these thatch huts it's
not defined as a city and everybody is just defined as an
individual house basically with the assumption that these are completely non-permanent and
therefore never constitute a city and never add on to a city.
מתיב רב חסדא, Masiv Rav Chisda, says רב חסדא Rav Chisda asks
on this, it says ויחנו על הירדן מבית הישימות, va-yachanu al ha-Yarden
mi-Beit ha-Yeshimot, the Jewish people they dwelled on the Jordan in from
the בית הישימות. Beit ha-Yeshimot. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה, Ve-amar Rabba
bar bar Chana, לדידי חזי לי ההוא אתרא, le-didi chazi li hahu
atra, I saw that place, the בית הישימות Beit ha-Yeshimot by the
Jordan river, והוי תלתא פרסי על תלתא פרסי, ve-havei tlata parsei al
tlata parsei, it was three פרסאות parsaot by three פרסאות. parsaot. A
פרסה parsa is four מיל, mil, a מיל mil is 2,000 אמות,
amot, a מיל mil is the תחום שבת. techum Shabbos. So therefore
that was 12 מיל mil by 12 מיל, mil, which by the
way is the basis for the רמב"ם Rambam who says that
the תחום שבת techum Shabbos biblically he says it is דאורייתא de-oraita
but it goes by 12 מיל, mil, it does not go by
one מיל, mil, 2,000 אמות, amot, it goes by 12 times, it's
based on that.
Anyway fine, moving on. So anyway it's 12 מיל mil by 12
מיל, mil, I saw that. ותניא Ve-tanya and we taught in the
ברייתא, Baraita, כשנפנין, keshenifnin, when the people had to go to the
bathroom, כשנפנין keshenifnin and particularly probably means defecate, אין נפנין לא לפניהם
ולא לצדיהם, ein nifnin lo lifneihem ve-lo litzdeihem, they didn't,
they had to leave the camp, right, the פסוק pasuk says it
says when you go out ויתד תהיה לך על אזנך והיה בשבתך
חוץ וחפרת בה ושבת וכסית את צאתך. ve-yated tihyeh lecha al azenecha
ve-haya be-shivtecha chutz ve-chafarta bah ve-shavta ve-chisita et tze'atecha. So
it specifically says you go outside the camp, you take care of
your needs, you cover up your excrement. So they did not go
to their in front of the camp or to the sides אלא
אחריהם, ela achareihem, but behind, because they didn't know where the camp
would be moving next but they apparently knew that it would not
be retracing their steps and going backwards. So therefore they didn't want
to walk over the place where they had just gone to the
bathroom. Okay now and אמר ליה רבא, amar leh Rava, so anyway
what's the relevance of all this? The relevance is that this is
considered to be their encampment even though all they lived in was
essentially huts, they lived in these tents were no more permanent than
the huts and nevertheless
it was this was considered the
מחנה ישראל. machaneh Yisrael. So how do you explain this?
So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה רבא, amar leh Rava, so
רבא Rava said back
to
him, דגלי מדבר קאמרת, diglei midbar kaamrat, you're talking about the
encampments in
the
desert,
כיון דכתיב על פי ה' יחנו ועל פי ה' יסעו, kevan de-chtiv
al pi Hashem yachanu ve-al pi Hashem yisau,
since they moved and settled and encamped by God's word, כמאן דקביעי
דמי, ke-man de-kavi'a dami, then they are considered permanent. And you could
say they're considered temporary anytime God says go you go, but also
as long as God said stay we're staying. So there's that sense
of and presumably as we'll see the realities of the idea of
thatch huts or actually more that nomads would inhabit because they were
a very type of a nomadic. presence. So therefore, normally it's not
considered part of making a city because it's an impermanent presence. But
here, as long as God said, it was permanent. By the way,
that's also relevant in other in other laws of שבת Shabbat where
the גמרא Gemara says like, how can we learn בניין Binyan from
the משכן? Mishkan? It's like, it's not a, you know, it's an
אוהל עראי ohel arai because they're constantly moving, it's never permanent. And
there's a similar answer is that since as long as God says
stay, you stay, so God said stay now, so for all so
now it's considered permanent. And so same basic point here. Okay, and
that's how they could go a whole 12 מיל mil to get
outside of the camp because it was all considered a city and
one location. אמר רב חיננא בר רב כהנא אמר רב אשי אם
יש שם שלוש חצרות או שני בתים הוא קבועה. Amar Rav Chinana
bar Rav Kahana amar Rav Ashi, im yesh sham shalosh chatzerot o
shenei battim, hu kevuah. If you have this city made of these
thatched huts, but there is a small section of it that is
considered to be, you know, a standard component of a city, which
is what? This idea we've seen before of three courtyards and each
courtyard has two houses, and here by houses it means permanent houses.
So if you have a component of the city that that is
permanent, then it is considered to be a city and presumably here
then that therefore even the thatched huts are constitute a extension of
the city. So according to this, the only problem before was when
the whole thing was made out of the thatched huts. But if
you actually have a city that has a lot of thatched huts
but it has a part of it that is permanent, then the
whole sit- then everything is considered part of the city. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב יושבי צריפין
ואוכלי מדברות, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, yoshei tzerifin ve-ochelei midbarot, those
that live in these thatched huts, we're going to make some general
comments about the nature of city life. So those that live in
these huts ואוכלי מדברות ve-ochelei midbarot and those that travel in the
wilderness, yes?
Is there- where some permanent houses and...
Yes, what the גמרא Gemara before it said that these thatched huts
don't count at all, but now the גמרא Gemara is sort of
reframing it and saying as long as there's the normal components of
a city that normally would define a city, which is three courtyards
with two houses and those are permanent houses. What about the חצרות?
chatzerot? חצרות Chatzerot are the courtyards, is
it because the houses are permanent or the fact that
they- they've built them in חצרות, chatzerot, like? Right, רש"י Rashi says
that the word בית bayit as opposed to צריפין tzerifin specifically means
permanent. So the way רש"י Rashi reads it is you do have
a small segment which is permanent, and then if you add to
that all these thatched huts, they also become an extension of the
city. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב יושבי צריפין ואוכלי מדברות, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, yoshei
tzerifin ve-ochelei midbarot, those that live in these thatched huts and those
that sort of travel in the desert, so it's basically people like
who live existences as nomads, חייהם אינם חיים, chayeihem einam chayim, their
lives are not their lives, meaning it's not, you know, it's not
real living. You know, they live- they live a life that doesn't
really have the normal types of amenities and basic sort of, you
know, creature comforts that make it a- that make it like a
normally pleasurable life. נשיהם ובניהם אינם שלהם, nesheihem u-veneihem einam shelahem, and
that's a pretty harsh comment. Their wives and their children are not
theirs, which basically as we'll see means that they have to be
concerned that their- that their children are not theirs and that their
wives are sleeping around. Now why the גמרא Gemara has that concern
we will see in a minute.
How about they sleeping around, they have a woman in every port?
That might be too, that's an excellent point. They might- they might
be sleeping around as well, but again from the perspective of the
man's concerns, his concerns is about his wife and his children. Yes,
but it's a very good point.
Are they talking meaning too?
I don't know. Well, they are because they're going to in a
minute talk about the מקווה, mikvah, so we'll take a look. You
know, and- I mean, I mean it's making it sort of obviously
as a certain rhetorical or exaggerated statement, but they're saying they're primitive.
It's sort of like somebody said- said a comment like this about
gypsies, you know? So, you know, who knows what- you know, how
could that really be a life, they're always moving and they're always-
and they're always sleeping around, they don't have a real type of
a, you know, established society. So it's- it's that type of a
statement.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. תניא, Tanya, תנא
ברייתא, tana baraita, תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, אלעזר איש בירייא
אומר יושבי צריפין כיושבי קברים. Elazar Ish Birayah omer, yoshei tzerifin ke-yoshei
kevarim. Those who dwell in these צריפין tzerifin it's like they're living
in the graveyard, okay, which means it's not a real life. ועל
בנותיהם הוא אומר, ve-al benoteihem hu omer, and regarding their daughters, which
means the women of them, their, you know, not- not just their
underage, it means the women, it says ארור שוכב עם כל בהמה.
Arur shochev im kol behemah. Oh my god, that's pretty harsh. What?
You mean in other cases true about the whole teaching, you know,
his position about teaching women תורה Torah and whatever. Okay, so he's
basically saying right, now if you just had
that maybe you would just say, you know, it means like, you
know, they're like not so civilized or something. But let's see what
the גמרא Gemara does with this. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי
טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason? Now the גמרא's Gemara understanding is
that what- well we'll see, well let's see the answer. עולא אמר
שאין להם מרחצאות. Ulla amar she-ein lahem merchata'ot. They don't have bathhouses.
You know, you have to have a city to build a nice
hot bathhouse. Otherwise, you know, I mean, you know, this was thanks
to the Romans we had these nice, you
know, bathhouses. But if you're
in the wilderness... But we're going to see that the גמרא Gemara
is going to say it's going back to this question about that
they sleep around because רבי יוחנן אמר מפני שמרגישים זה לזה בטבילה.
Rabbi Yochanan amar mipnei shemargishim zeh lazeh bitvila.
They're aware of one another when they go out to the מקווה.
mikvah. So what does all this have to do? So רש״י Rashi
basically says since they don't have bathhouses when they have to bathe
they go way out to the river. You're going out to the
river all alone, nobody else is around, so that's a place that
you can have these trysts and encounters. And the idea of going
to the מקווה, mikvah, רש״י Rashi says it's interesting because it says
that
because they're not private about it and they're going presumably outside the
city as well and then it becomes public they're going to the
מקווה, mikvah, so maybe some unscrupulous man finds out and figures that
he'll be able to seduce them or something right after they come
out of the מקווה. mikvah. Something of that nature. So then it
says let's take a look. It says like this מאי בינייהו mai
beinaihu what's the difference between these two concerns? איכא בינייהו נהרא דסמיך
לבירתא ika beinaihu nahara desamich labirta if the river is close to
the city so there would still be a מקווה mikvah concern but
there would not be the concern about the bathhouses because when they
went to bathe at least they were not able to be in
private. So anyway a big clearly the perspective
of some of the תנאים Tannaim here
that whatever that people that live these lives it was not a
decent life and a concern about their general morality of the women,
which is disturbing. So now the גמרא Gemara continues, אמר רב הונא
כל עיר שאין בה ירק Amar Rav Huna kol ir she'ein bah
yerek now that we're talking about components of what it means to
be living in a city so we talked about not having a
nomadic existence. We say other important components of a city. Any city
that does not have vegetables available אין תלמיד חכם רשאי לדור בה
ein talmid chacham rashai ladur bah a תורה Torah sage shouldn't live
there because vegetables presumably are a nice easy form of sustenance and
inexpensive and therefore it's important for תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim who obviously
are investing a lot of their time learning that they have available
to them vegetables. So the גמרא Gemara says למימרא דיירק מעליא lemeimra
deyerek ma'alya this suggests that vegetables are good for your health
or good. והתניא שלשה מרבים את הזבל וכופפים את הקומה ונוטלים אחד
מחמש מאות ממאור עיניו של אדם Vehatanya shelosha marbim et hazevel vechofefim
et hakoma venotlim echad mechamesh me'ot mim'or einav shel adam three things
increase the excrement, bend down your stature, make you sort of hunched
over and take away one five-hundredth of your eyesight. So these three
things are not good for your
health. ואלו הן ve'elu hen top of נ״ו עמוד א׳ Nun Vav
Amud Alef these are they: פת קיבר pat kibar so it is
like coarse bran bread, ושכר חדש veshechar chadash and new mead, beer,
וירק veyerek and vegetables. So you see vegetables are not good. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult, הא
בתומא וכרתי ha betuma vecharti one is with garlic and leeks, הא
בשאר ירקי ha bish'ar yarkei the other is other vegetables. So which
is which? So רש״י Rashi first says that the garlic and leeks
are not good for you and then he says actually it's the
other way. Garlic and leeks are good for you, which is clearly
garlic and leeks are also a lot of what gives taste to
food. Garlic and leeks, at least, garlic's actually one of the healthiest
vegetables or food, aren't they? Garlic, whatever it is. Anyway, it's supposed
to be extremely good for you, garlic. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says כדתניא kidtanya like we
taught in a ברייתא Beraita שום ירק shum yerek garlic is a
vegetable. כרישין krishin which is what do they call that, cress? Or
something. כרישין krishin what? Leeks?
Leeks.
Okay. Oh yeah, כרתי karti excuse me, that's the כרתי karti from
before. כרישין חצי ירק krishin chatsi yerek is half a
vegetable. נירא צנון נירא סם חיים nira tzenon nira sam chayim if
you've seen a
radish then you see the sap of life. Okay. So whatever. והתניא
Vehatanya but didn't we teach in
a ברייתא Beraita נירא צנון נירא סם מות nira tzenon nira sam
mavet that actually it's sort of the draught of death? So לא
קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult, כאן בעלים כאן באמהות kan be'alim
kan be'imahot one is with the leaves and the other is with
the actual bulbs themselves. כאן בימות החמה כאן בימות הגשמים kan biyemot
hachamah kan biyemot hageshamim and it also depends on whether it's the
summer or the winter in terms of trying to figure out which
is which. Okay fine. Anyway, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav back to the הלכות halachot of תחומין. techumin. כל
עיר שיש בה מעלות ומורדות kol ir sheyesh bah ma'alot umordot or
actually not back to תחומין, techumin, back to comments about the aspects
of a city that make for good life or bad life. כל
עיר שיש בה מעלות ומורדות kol ir sheyesh bah ma'alot umordot any
city that has in it sort of rises and declines, meaning a
very hilly city. Adam, I don't know my wife comes from Pittsburgh,
that is so hilly in Pittsburgh. That's like walking in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
So anyway, every any place that has that has a lot of,
you know, inclines, a lot of ups and downs, a lot of
hills, אדם ובהמה שבה מתים בחצי ימיהם. Adam u-veheimah she-bah meitim ba-chatzi
yemeihem. So people and the animals in it it's so exerting on
you that you live only half your life. So the גמרא Gemara
says מתים סלקא דעתך, Meitim salka daatach, literally, literally you only you
die at half your
age? No. אלא אימא מזקינים בחצי ימיהם, Ella eima mizkinim ba-chatzi yemeihem,
you get old, you know, when you're still in your middle age.
It's so funny because nowadays we would say, you know, it's good,
a lot of exercise, you know, whatever. I actually, you know, whatever,
kept was much healthier when I was in when I when I
spent time in like ירושלים Yerushalayim because you're always walking up and
down and up and down, it's really good for you. All right
anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע הני מיליאתא דבי
בירי ודבי נרש, Amar Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua hanei milyata de-vei
Beiri ve-de-vei Narash, those hills in the place of Beiri and Narash,
which are two towns, אזקנון, azkunun, they got me old, they made
me old. So that's consistent with what we said before. Okay. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabanan, now back to the הלכות halachot of תחומים. techumin.
בא לרבעה, Ba lereivah, when you're coming to square off the city,
מרבעה בריבוע עולם, mereiva be-reibua olam, you square it off to the
compass points, the sides of the compass. So I did remember to
bring my little pictures here. I don't have enough to go around,
but you can share.
Here.
So you see here's what we got. There's Manhattan. Look what happens
when you square it off to the to the directions. You see
how much you get? Right? You get you know
major chunk here of New Jersey and all of this part of,
what is that, Queens? Yeah, Queens and a little bit of Brooklyn.
Queens and a little bit of Brooklyn.
Okay. So that's what you get when you square it off. You
get a lot, right? And all of that is before you add
your אלפיים אמות, alpayim amot, which gives you another like three-fifths of
a mile, another kilometer. Two thousand אמות amot by the way, good
rule of thumb is roughly a kilometer. So that's after you get
your city, you have a kilometer outside your city. Yes.
So this is a problem for the people in Manhattan who walk
to the Bronx on שבת. Shabbat.
Well that was the point that Dove made yesterday, which was that
if you start in the Bronx, then the Bronx overlaps with Manhattan.
All on the west side. Because you can see the Central Park
lake, that's the dark spot in the middle of Manhattan.
It's an interesting question. Well if you start but if the if
you're in the Bronx, then it goes all the way down to
what's this thing that's what's this little what's this protrusion here? What's
this?
That is oh that's Randall's Island.
Okay.
So
if you start in the Bronx
which is actually not connected to the Bronx.
Okay. You get up to up to Randall's Island, right? But you're
say but you're saying even if you make the תחום techum there,
you don't get to the upper we you don't you don't get
to the to the upper west side.
You don't, you would get to part of the upper west side.
Uh-huh. Except that except that you don't go as far west.
Right. That's an interesting question. Maybe it's again, maybe the bridge, the
Broadway bridge, you know, maybe gets back to that whole question about
if there's a house connected to the bridge, does the bridge count
as well? It's a good question. I'll have to I'll have to
think about that. Yeah. Okay. So that's what you get when you
square it off. Thank you to Google. All right. So now it
says, so back to the גמרא. Gemara. נותן צפונה לצפון עולם, Notin
tzafonah le-tzafono shel olam, you make the northern extension the north, you
know, דרומה לדרום עולם, deromah le-deromo shel olam, the south the south,
you know, and you basically take the southernmost point northernmost point and
whatever and you and you make a square it off or rectangle
it off. Now וסימנך, ve-simanach, and the way to know which is
which is עגלה egla because how did you tell directions before you
had magnetic
compasses? So עגלה בצפון, egla be-tzafon, the calf is in the north,
which means Ursa Major is the and that had the north star,
so that's in the north. ועקרב בדרום, ve-akrav be-darom, and the scorpion
is in the south. That's again the constellation. Apparently according to Soncino,
the scorpion is not due south, but it is in the south
if you're in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. It's also not always visible
as opposed to the north star which is always visible. רבי יוסי
אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, Rabbi Yosi says, אם איני יודע לרבעה בריבוע
של עולם,
im eini yodeia lereivah bi-reibua
shel olam, if you don't know how to do this, meaning you
don't know the constellations, מרבעה כמין התקופה, mereivah ke-min ha-tekufah, then you
can do it based on the season and the rising and setting
of the sun. כיצד, Keitzad, how? חמה יוצאה ביום ארוך ושוקעת ביום
ארוך, Chama yotza be-yom aroch ve-shokaat be-yom aroch, when it rises on
a long day and sets on a long day, meaning like at
the, you know, summer solstice, the longest day of the year, זו
פני צפון, zehu pnei tzafon, that's the north. וחמה יוצאה ביום קצר
ושוקעת ביום קצר, ve-chama yotza be-yom katzar ve-shokaat be-yom katzar, in the
winter solstice, when it's the shortest day of the year and it
rises on a short day and sets on a short day, זו
פני דרום, zehu pnei darom, that is the south. What does that
mean? So again, did a little did a little searching on the
web, found a nice little picture. Oh yeah,
Tropic
of Cancer, Tropic of Capricorn. Right.
Thank you. Okay, so look at that. So what happens during the
vernal and autumnal equinox, the sun rises due east and sets due
west and it always is moving towards the south, okay? By the
way, here's a little interesting thing. The names of the directions are
what's north is צפון, Tzafon, some say it means צפון Tzafun because
the head is hidden. The head never appears there. Okay, and some
say דרום Darom means like דר רם, dar ram, that's where the
sun dwells in its height. The sun always moves to the south
if you're in the Northern Hemisphere. Okay, so at the autumnal and
vernal equinox, it is rising due east and sets due west. On
the long
days, it rises from the
northeast and sets northwest and on the short days, it rises from
southeast and sets southwest, right? If you just think about it, if
it's a long day, if it's always moving towards the south, so
if you start further north, it's going to be a longer path.
So on the longer days, it starts more to the north, it
starts in the northeast. Okay, but if you also notice, it never
gets more than like 23 degrees to the north. So the sun
will never rise or to the south. So the sun will never
rise like at exactly at northeast. Even on the longest day, it's
going to be halfway till northeast. All right, but when it says
פני צפון pnei Tzafon or פני דרום, pnei Darom, it means the
direction that it's moving is like pointing towards the north or pointing
towards the south. It's very funny 'cause you would think the easier
thing to say is on the autumnal or vernal equinox it's due
east and due west and just make a 90-degree angle and you
know your north and south. So it's not exactly clear to me
why it's important to work with north and south rather than east
and west. Okay, so anyway, so that's what he says. ותקופת תשרי,
v'tkufat Tishrei, no, I'm
sorry, so no, actually it does say the last part of it,
ותקופת תשרי, v'tkufat Tishrei, so I spoke too soon, ותקופת תשרי, v'tkufat
Tishrei, so that תקופת תשרי tkufat Tishrei is the vernal equinox, חמה
יוצאה בחצי מזרח ושוקעת בחצי מערב. chama yotza b'chatzi mizrach v'shoka'at b'chatzi
ma'arav. There it's exactly due east and due west. So the best
way to figure it out is to go, you know, the vernal
or autumnal equinox, like ניסן Nissan or תשרי, Tishrei, and then you'd
run a 90-degree angle. But on the shortest and longest days, it
moves, it's towards the north or towards the
south. שנאמר, shene'emar, and we see this in the פסוק pasuk because
the פסוק pasuk says, הולך אל דרום וסובב אל צפון, holech el
darom v'sovev el tzafon, the sun goes towards the north and circles
back towards the south... goes towards the south, excuse me, and circles
back towards the north. הולך אל דרום ביום, holech el darom bayom,
so the sun is always moving towards the south in the day.
The sun rises in the east, heads southward, and sets in the
west. וסובב אל צפון v'sovev el tzafon and goes back to the
north בלילה, balaila, right, at the night, right, because look at it,
right, it's an ellipse. So it goes towards the south in the
day and circles back towards the north, you know, at night. Look
at your nice little picture there. All right, very nice.
סובב סובב הולך הרוח, sovev sovev holech haruach, round and round goes
the wind, אלו פני מזרח ופני מערב. elu pnei mizrach u'pnei ma'arav.
This is the face of the east and the face of the
west, meaning sometimes the רוח, ruach, the direction moves
and you know, in terms of sometimes it goes to the east
direction, sometimes to the west direction. I'm sorry, not east and west,
did I say that right? Yes, פני מזרח ופני מערב. pnei mizrach
u'pnei ma'arav. I'm sorry, hold on one second,
פעמים מהלכתן ופעמים מסבבתן. pa'amim mahalachtan u'pa'amim mesovevatan. Right, I'm sorry, I
said that wrong. Anyway, this is the east and the west, sometimes
it goes in the east and the west and sometimes it goes
around them. It's not exactly clear what that means, but basically the
point being that
basically it means that in the day... yeah, not exactly sure. I
mean,
anyway, because I mean it rises in the east in the day
and it sets in the west at night, but exactly what it
means sometimes it goes and sometimes it goes around them. Anyway, not...
I tried to figure out exactly what רש"י Rashi was getting at,
but okay, let's move on. The גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר
רב משרשיא ליתנהו להני כללי. amar Rav Mesharshaya leitnehu l'hanei klalei. Ah,
these are not really these are not really good rules. דתניא, d'tanya,
we saw in a ברייתא, Beraita, לא יצאה חמה מעולם מקרן מזרחית
צפונית, lo yatza chama me'olam mikeren mizrachit tzfonit, the sun never really
rose truly from the northeast and שקעה בקרן מערבית צפונית v'shaka b'keren
ma'aravit tzfonit and never truly set in the northwest. ולא
יצאה חמה מקרן מזרחית דרומית v'lo yatza chama mikeren mizrachit dromit and
it never really rose from the southeast and שקעה בקרן מערבית דרומית
v'shaka b'keren ma'aravit dromit and set in the southwest, which seems to
be the point that I said before, which is while in the
summer it's more towards the north and in the winter it's more
towards the south, it's never due northeast or due southeast. So it
says you can't really use this, even though it's more northernly or
more southernly, you can't really tell what north and south are based
on where the sun is. Okay, אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, now says
שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel was very big in astronomy. So says
שמואל, Shmuel, אין תקופת ניסן נופלת אלא בארבעה רבעי היום. ein tkufat
Nissan nofelet ela b'arba'a riv'ei hayom. Equal when the day is 12
hours. Okay, so those are the seasons in which you know the
weather is more between the extremes.
Winter and summer, so those are the extremes, and solstice, which just
sol means sun, but anyway, those are the days which are the
longest day and the shortest day of the year. So those four
points, right, midpoint and the extremes, are considered to be the תקופות,
tekufos, the you know, the set sort of points, seasonal points. So
ניסן, Nissan, the תקופה tekufa of ניסן Nissan and תשרי Tishrei is
vernal and autumnal equinox, and the תקופה tekufa of
טבת Teves and תמוז Tammuz is
the winter and
the and the summer solstice, okay? Got it? טבת Teves winter and
תמוז Tammuz in the summer. Okay, so right, שבעה עשר בתמוז Shiva
Asar B'Tammuz always very hot. Alright, so now, and חנוכה Chanukah time
it always gets very
cold. So those are the four points. So now שמואל Shmuel says,
אין תקופת ניסן, ein tekufas Nissan, which is the vernal equinox, נופלת
אלא בארבעה ריבי היום, nofeles ela be'arba'ah rivei hayom,
only comes at the four quarters of the day. What does that
mean? או בתחילת היום, o b'tchilas hayom, either at start of at
sunrise, או בתחילת הלילה, o b'tchilas halailah, or sunset or the beginning
of night, או בחצי היום, o b'chatzi hayom, or it comes at
noon, או בחצי הלילה, o b'chatzi halailah, or it comes at midnight.
Now what does this mean? It's okay, it's very easy. What is
the shift from one year's vernal you know any of those points,
but one year's vernal equinox to the next? Well, what is the
shift
by the Julian calendar would be six hours. What? 365 and one
quarter.
365 and one quarter days. So what's the shift in terms of,
you know, moving from the time of day and time of week?
It's one day later of the next year, one and a quarter
days later right from the previous year, right? If this year it
was Monday at 6:00 a.m., so that same point where the sun
will be next year will be 52 weeks plus one and a
quarter days. So it'll be Tuesday at what's a quarter day? How
many hours? Six hours. So Tuesday at noon. And then the next
year it's going to be Wednesday at six hours, Wednesday at sunset.
And then the next year it's going to be Thursday at midnight.
And then it's going to be Friday at sunrise. So that's what
שמואל Shmuel says, assuming
that the vernal equinox began, you know, that there's a starting point
where it began at sunrise, it's always going to be either sunrise,
noon, sunset, or midnight. Because you always add a day and six
hours. So it's going to be every half hour on the half
hour as it were. Yes, every half day on the half day.
And that calculation is actually used for ברכת החמה Birkas HaChammah every
28 years.
Exactly. Okay, so now we continue.
ואין תקופת תמוז נופלת. ve'ein tekufas Tammuz nofeles. Now if if ניסן
Nissan is starts on sunrise, so the next תקופה
tekufa is how much of a shift? So it's a quarter of
a year, right? Everybody with me here? So a quarter of a
year. So if we had an extra day and a half, you
know, is the extra for a whole year, what's the extra for
a quarter of that? So a day is 24 hours, that's 6
hours. Half of a day is 6 hours, divided by 4 is
an hour and a half. So it's seven and a half hours.
So the move from one תקופה tekufa to the next is a
seven and a half hour move. So if so therefore תקופת תמוז
tekufas Tammuz will always happen אלא או באחת ומחצה. ela o b'achas
u'mechtza. So if you started from midnight, which we know was one
of the times the vernal equinox could be, so midnight plus seven
and a half hours gets you right
7:30 in the morning. That's an hour and a half into the
day. Yes? So either one and a half hours or או בשבע
ומחצה o b'sheva u'mechtza בין ביום בין בלילה. bein bayom bein balailah.
Now from now if once you have one תקופה tekufa start point,
every תקופה tekufa moves, you know, in you know moves in itself
a six-hour shift. Right? We've already established that the movement of a
תקופה tekufa from one year to the next is a day and
six hours. Yes? Everybody with me? That we established that for the
vernal equinox. You know same is true about the summer solstice. The
shift from one year to the next is a day and six
hours. So since the summer solstice according to the גמרא Gemara began
started can come at one and a half hours, it can also
come at into the day meaning 7:30 in whatever, it can also
come at
plus six, seven and a half hours, right? At 1:30 p.m. And
then you add another six, what happens when you add another six
to 1:30 p.m.? What do you get? 7:30 p.m. which is one
and a half hours into the night. Then you add another six
and you get 1:30 a.m. right so that's seven and a half
hours into. in the night, and then you’re back to an hour
and a half in the day. Okay, so the summer solstice is
either at one and a half hours into the day and seven
and a half hours into the day or one and a half
in the night and seven and a half in the night. All
right, אלא באחד ומחצה או בשבעה ומחצה בין ביום ובין בלילה. ela
b’echad umachetza o b’shiva umachetza bein b’yom uvein balaila. ואין תקופת תשרי,
vein tekufat tishrei,
now you add seven and a half hours to that to get
to the autumnal equinox, so that’s נופלת או בשלוש שעות או בתשע
שעות. nofeles o b’shalosh sha’os o b’teisha sha’os. Okay, it’s either three
hours into the day or nine hours into the day, בין ביום
ובין בלילה, bein b’yom uvein balaila, whether day or night. You can
do the math yourself. But basically, the easy point is since you’re
going to add seven and a half hours and the six sort
of just as a shift to the next point, it’s just adding
an hour and a half. So from going from one and a
half or seven and a half, we now went to three or
to nine into the day or night. ואין תקופת טבת, vein tekufat
teves, add another one and a half hours to our starting point,
נופלת או בארבע ומחצה, nofeles o b’arba umachetza, so from three we
get to four and a half hours into the day, או בעשר
ומחצה, o b’eser umachetza, or ten and a half hours into the
day, בין ביום ובין בלילה, bein b’yom uvein balaila, whether day or
night. All right, so you roughly get that. I didn’t do the
whole math for the rest, but you see how that works. ואין
בין תקופה לתקופה, vein bein tekufa letekufa, this is what I was
telling you before, from one תקופה tekufa to the next, a quarter
year, from autumnal to to, you know, to the winter solstice, from
the winter solstice to the vernal, from the vernal to the summer
solstice, אלא, ela, so the distance between one תקופה tekufa and the
next, an exact quarter of a year, תשעים ואחד ושבע שעות ומחצה,
tishim ve’echad vesheva sha’os umachetza, is 91 and seven hours and a
half, 91 days, seven hours and a half. Okay, so do the
math: 91 times four is 364, right? So good, so that’s 52
weeks. So seven and a half times four is, so seven times
four is 28 plus a half is two, 30, which is one
day and a quarter. So there you go, 365 and a quarter
days. ואין, vein, by the way, just so people don't know, the
problem with the Julian calendar was not 365 and a quarter, clearly
they knew 365 and a quarter, that's what שמואל Shmuel knows. The
problem with the Julian calendar is that it is actually less than
365 and a quarter. The only switch of the Gregorian calendar was
that we do not have a leap year every hundredth year, unless
it’s year 400, and then we do have a leap year. So
it’s actually off by by
three days every 400 years, the Julian calendar. So the correction is
not to have a leap year for three out of the four
of the hundred years, so every hundred years that’s not 400, we
don’t have a leap year, which is why in the year 2000
we did have a leap year, yes.
Yeah, our permanent calendar actually more better matched the solar year on
average over the 19-year cycle than the Julian calendar did, which is
very
impressive. Second, the Qumran community did not follow these calendarical rules, they
had a 364-day, I know, okay.
Yes, I
one question just keeps standing out of my mind, they obviously had
very sophisticated knowledge, so I’m wondering why they didn’t look at the
northern circumpolar constellations and Well,
they did, that’s what it said before. It said it said it
said you look at the Ursa Major and you have that’s the
North Star, I mean didn’t say the North Star, but that’s what
it said
before.
Ursa Minor, Ursa Major, the outer Well,
it said the עגלה, agala, I don’t know if עגלה agala meant
Ursa Minor, Ursa Major.
Here the note here says it means Taurus.
Yeah, well, that would totally be off, so I was going by
Steinsaltz who said it meant Ursa Major or Minor, I think he
said it was Major, but anyway.
They probably they probably they probably meant Ursa Minor.
Anyway, but they did have the constellations. It’s funny because it said
you know because it says if you can’t do the constellations, here’s
how you can do it by sunrise sunset. But it is so
easy sunrise sunset if you go to vernal or autumnal equinox, you
know. Okay, so now it says like this, ואין תקופה מושכת מחברתה
אלא חצי שעה, vein tekufa mosheches mechavartah ela chatzi sha’ah,
that we already saw, that the shift of from one year from
to the next of when let’s say the vernal equinox occurs is
a going to be six hours after you know because it’s a
day and a half shift of the previous year, so it’ll be
six-hour difference in the day when that equinox point will occur or
solstice point will occur. ואמר שמואל, ve’amar Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel says,
אין לך תקופת ניסן שנופלת בצדק, ein lacha tekufat nissan shenofeles b’tzedek,
now the this idea that the exact point, right, it’s exactly like
one particular minute in the day, the exact moment of the vernal
of the of the vernal equinox, that never occurs בצדק, b’tzedek, whenever
it occurs בצדק, b’tzedek, שאינה משברת אילנות, she’eina meshaberes ilanos,
so it never occurs in צדק tzedek and it doesn’t cause the
trees to be broken. So according, you know, apparently when it would
fall under Jupiter because they also had these, you know, seven constellations
or whatever, stars, whatever, a different one each day, I don’t exactly
get how it works but I mean I sort of do but
anyway. Okay, so whenever that equinox fell under Jupiter, it would be
very bad, be very maybe windy and the trees would break.
And טבת Tevet never falls in צדק; Tzedek; it would never fall
in, you know, that when טבת Tevet fell in צדק Tzedek it
would always lead to a drying up of the seeds; it would
never fall in צדק Tzedek without the seeds drying up. והוא דשלי
לבנה או בלבנה או בצדק Ve-hu deshali levana o bi-levana o be-tzedek
and that's only when the sun is in a, you know, is
in ascendancy or, you know, either under the moon, I mean, the
moon is in ascendancy under the moon constellation or under Jupiter. I
have no idea what that's about. Okay. But anyway, the other part
I got. Okay. Moving on.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. So now we think okay enough
math, but not so. You can see the pictures to see what's
coming up. But actually this is going to be quite easy because
I assume that that base, you know, whatever, that this type of
math is pretty accessible. תנו רבנן המרבע את העיר, Tanu Rabbanan ha-merubeia
et ha-ir, if you square off the city, עושה אותה כמין טבלה
מרובעת, oseh otah kemin tavla meruba'at, again you make it like a
square tableau. וחוזר ומרבע את התחומין, Ve-chozer u-merubeia et ha-tchumin, and then
the תחומין tchumin you go ahead and you make a bigger square
around that square or rectangle. ועושה
אותן כמין טבלה מרובעת, Ve-oseh otan kemin tavla meruba'at, and you also
make them like a square tableau. וכשהוא מודד, U-cheshehu moded, when you
measure, לא ימדוד מאמצע הקרן אלפיים אמה, lo yimdod me-emtza ha-keren alpayim
amah, don't measure at an angle from the corner 2000 אמה, amah,
מפני שהוא מפסיד את
הזויות, mipnei she-hu mafsid et ha-zaviyot, because you'll lose the corners. Meaning,
here's your city. Okay. So first thing you do is you square
it off, right, and you gain the corners. And then when you
make the new, what do you call it, when you make the
תחום tchum at a mile away, at about a kilometer away, so
you do, you also make a bigger square, right, 2000 אמה amah
from this point and 2000 from this and 2000 from this. So
it says, don't measure 2000 אמה amah here because if you measure
2000 אמה amah from the corner, you're going to get a much
smaller square. Okay? You don't get the gain you get of the
corners, which gets you a lot more than 2000 אמה, amah, it
gets you 2000 times the square root of two, right? Everybody knows
the math, right? Times 1.4 roughly. Okay. So like, does everybody know
the math? Right, if you have, if you know, right, 1, 1,
square root of
two, a squared plus b squared equals c squared, right? So that
so if it's a square, right, if it's a rectangle it won't
be that way, but if it's a square, right, so this is
1, 1, that's going to be the square root of two of
whatever, you know, of whatever that side is.
So that's why ישיבה yeshiva boys need to learn math.
So that would be right. So the corner, don't measure from the
corner at an angle because you get much more of a corner,
you get 2000 times the square root of two. Okay. So it
says, מפני שהוא מפסיד את הזויות, mipnei she-hu mafsid et ha-zaviyot, אלא
מביא טבלה מרובעת שהיא אלפיים אמה על אלפיים אמה. ela meivi tavla
meruba'at she-hi alpayim amah al alpayim amah. You get a square tableau
of 2000 by 2000. It's not really 2000 by 2000 because it's
2000 by 2000 plus the, you know, added to the inner square.
But
anyway, ומניחה בקרן באלכסונה, u-menichah be-keren be-alachsonah, and you put it in
the corner at the angle. נמצאת עיר משתכרת ארבע מאות אמה לכאן
וארבע מאות אמה לכאן. nimtzet ir mis-takeret arba me'ot amah le-kan ve-arba
me'ot amah le-kan. נמצאו תחומין משתכרין שמונה מאות אמה לכאן ושמונה מאות
אמה לכאן. nimtzu tchumin mis-takerin shemonah me'ot amah le-kan u-shemonah me'ot amah
le-kan.
So what this is is we're assuming that the city is,
one minute, right,
we're assuming the city is basically 1000 אמה. amah. Okay. So if
the city is 1000 אמה, amah, okay. So therefore how much do
you gain? Let's start
here. How much do you gain because you've made a square here?
How much is the extra, you know, is this more than 2000?
So this is 2000 times the square root of two, which is
roughly times 1.4 is 2800. So you gained 800 אמה amah because
you've gone at least because you, you know, because of that angle.
That angle is 800 more than if you had made a circle
of 2000 אמה. amah. Now how much have you gained here because
of what you've
added? So this is
so this is I said it wrong, I'm sorry. This is also
assuming 2000 across, so therefore the radius is 1000. Okay? Right? Yes.
So the radius is 1000, it's also 2000 across. So how much
have you gained here? How much is this? So if this is
1000 and this is 1000, this is 1000 times the square root
of two, which is 1400. So here if the city is 2000,
you gain 400 because you made the square, and the תחום tchum
which is another 2000, you gain 800 because you made a square
rather than a circle. Yes, clear? Okay. So it says, so let's
read that again. נמצאת עיר. nimtzet ir. So, let's read again from
אלא, ela, like six lines down. אלא מביא טבלה מרובעת שהיא אלפיים
אמה על אלפיים אמה. ela meivi tavla meruba'at she-hi alpayim amah al
alpayim amah. The city is 2,000 by 2,000. And the תחום t'chum
which is another 2,000 you gain 800 because you made a square
rather than a circle. Yes? Clear? Okay. So it says, so let's
read that again: נמצא עיר. Nimtza ir. So let's read again from
אלא ella like six lines down: אלא מביא טבלא מרובעת כאלפיים אמה
על אלפיים אמה. ella mevi tavla meruba'at k'alpayim amma al alpayim amma.
Oh, so now it makes sense. I think the טבלא tavla is
for the city, not for the תחום t'chum yet. We're assuming the
city is 2,000 אמות amot across. So you bring a square that's
2,000 by 2,000 ומניחה בקרן אלכסונה u'm'nicha b'keren alchasona
and you put it in the corner which basically just means that
you align it so that the so that it's squared off. נמצא
עיר משתכרת ארבע מאות אמה לכאן וארבע מאות אמה לכאן, Nimtza ir
mishtakeret arba me'ot amma l'kan v'arba me'ot amma l'kan, so the city
by being squared off got an extra 400 אמה amma in the
corners. ונמצא תחומים, v'nimtza tchumim, and now the תחום tchum which is
2,000 אמות amot in every direction, now the 1,000 משתכרין שמונה מאות
אמה לכאן ושמונה מאות אמה לכאן mishtakrin shmoneh me'ot amma l'kan u'shmoneh
me'ot amma l'kan
gets an extra 800 אמה amma over the 2,000 when you go
at the corners at the angles. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says נמצא עיר ותחומיה משתכרין אלף ומאתים
לכאן ואלף ומאתים לכאן. Nimtza ir u'tchumeha mishtakrin elef u'matayim l'kan v'elef
u'matayim l'kan.
So therefore because you did this squaring on both parts, the city
and the תחום, tchum, you can go 1,200 extra אמות amot if
you're going at a 45 degree angle, right? So if you go
straight this way you get 3,000, right? And if you go this
is easy also, you go straight this way you get 3,000, right?
So if you go this way you get 3,000 times square root
of 2 which is 4,200 so you gain an extra 1,200 when
you go at an angle. All right.
Yeah. Right. Because this is 1,000 plus
2,000 so this is also 3,000.
Right. Okay. All right. So by going at an angle because of
the corners when you go that way you get an extra 1,200.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר אביי ומשכחת לה
במתא דהויא תרי אלפי אתרי אלפי. Amar Abaye u'mashkachat la b'mata d'hava
trei alfi a'trei alfi. Like I told you that's assuming the city
is 2,000 by 2,000 it's a circle and therefore that gets to
that math. תניא, Tanya, now we've learned in a ברייתא: Beraita: אמר
רבי אליעזר בן רבי יוסי תחום ערי לויים אלפיים אמה. Amar Rabbi
Eliezer ben Rabbi Yossi tchum arei Levi'im alpayim amma. So the cities
of the לויים, Levi'im, the תורה Torah says you're given 2,000 אמות
amot around which is our basis for this. But it also says
that they have a מגרש, migrash, an area that is like unplanted,
they have fields 2,000 אמות, amot, but of the 2,000 the first
1,000 is unplanted. So the cities of the לויים Levi'im
right basically was whatever the size of the city is and we'll
worry about that in a minute. So first the תורה Torah says
you give them 2,000 אמות. amot. Okay but then it says in
another place you give but not another place right there, but it
also says a thousand אמות. amot. So חז"ל Chazal understood that the
first 1,000 אמות amot was מגרש, migrash, this is basically just like
open field like open whatever like parks or whatever, and then this
is שדות sadot which is this is where they planted their grain
and whatever. Okay so these are these are fields for grain and
then but the first 1,000 here you're standing in grain whatever. Okay
but this is just open, all right? So as you can already
see by this you've got 1,000 and 1,000 the שדות sadot there's
much more area to the fields than there is to the מגרש
migrash because it's a bigger square. Yes? That clear? Okay. So let's
see what he says. תחום ערי לויים אלפיים אמה צא מהם אלף
אמה מגרש. Tchum arei Levi'im alpayim amma tze mehem elef amma migrash.
The first אלף elef is for the מגרש. migrash. נמצא מגרש רביע.
Nimtza migrash revia. So the מגרש migrash is only a quarter of
the whole והשאר שדות וכרמים v'hashar sadot u'chramim and the rest are
fields and vineyards. Okay that's looking because that doesn't look like it's
a quarter. I mean we'll do the math but I think it's
probably not a quarter and the גמרא's Gemara going to ask that.
מנא הני מילי? Mina hanei mili? Where do you get this from?
אמר רבא דאמר קרא, Amar Rava d'amar kra, the פסוק passuk says:
מקיר העיר וחוצה אלף אמה סביב. mikira ha'ir v'chutza elef amma saviv.
So one thing says 2,000 but another פסוק passuk says a thousand.
So אמר תורה Amar Torah סביב העיר באלף, saviv ha'ir b'elef, a
thousand outside the city. נמצא מגרש. Nimtza migrash. So נמצא מגרש רביע.
Nimtza migrash revia. So therefore so now the גמרא Gemara so I'm
sorry so
אמר תורה Amar Torah סביב העיר באלף saviv ha'ir b'elef period. So
first we learn from the פסוק passuk that there is a מגרש
migrash that goes 1,000 out of the 2,000. Now the גמרא Gemara
goes back to quote the ברייתא Beraita
and it says נמצא מגרש רביע. Nimtza migrash revia. The מגרש migrash
is a quarter. רביע? revia? A quarter? פלגא הוי? palga hava? It's
half. And it's not half either but it didn't do the math.
So it was just assuming if it's 2,000 and 1,000 is the
מגרש, migrash, that's half of 2,000. So it's not half, but it's
also not a quarter. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer
is. אמר רבא
בר רב אדא
משוחאה אסברה לי. Amar Rava bar Rav Adda meshuacha asbra li. The
measurers explained to me, which is interesting which or a measurer which
רש"י Rashi says means one of the guys that measures the תחומים.
tchumim. So people who actually know the math and do this for
a living explained to me that here's how it works. Okay. משכחת
לה במתא דהויא תרי אלפי אתרי אלפי. meshkachat la b'mata d'hava trei
alfi a'trei alfi. The city is 2,000 by 2,000. תחום כמה הוי?
tchum kama hava? שיתסר. shitsar. קרנותיה כמה הוי שיתסר. karnoteha kama hava
shitsar. So if the city is 2,000 by 2,000 okay then the
תחום tchum which is to get to here right is also is
Explain to me that here's how it works, okay? משכחת לה במסכתא
דהוה תרי אלפי על תרי אלפי, Mishkachat lah be-masechta dahava try alphei
al try alphei, the city is two thousand by two thousand. תחום
כמה הוה? שיתסר. קרנותא כמה הוה? שיתסר. Tchum kamma hava? Shitser. Kronota
kamma hava? Shitser.
So if the city is two thousand by two thousand,
okay, then the תחום, tchum, which is to get to here, right,
is also is another, right, you add another two thousand to get
there. Now,
let's go, so what's the entire area across? If this is, if
this is two thousand, right, and each one of these are two
thousand, what's the entire area
across? Eight thousand, thanks for paying attention, by eight thousand. Okay so
now we are going to divide these up in order to find
the square footage as it were, we're going to divide them up
by square feet, by square units of a thousand by a thousand.
So how many
square, you know,
whatever, feet are there, calling that a foot. So they're so okay
so if it's here there's going to be how many? By the
city there will be right there'll be two because the city is
two thousand by two thousand, right? Yes? By city there'll be two,
okay here there's another two thousand, two more, here there'll be two,
okay right another two thousand, okay so and then here there's two,
yes? People with me here? Because it's two here, two, here's it's
going to be another two thousand so it's going to be another
two, okay this will be so not to the proportion, another two,
there that's what you get. This is two thousand, two thousand okay
got that? More or less you saw this right? So how many
do we have? So if we count just not the corners, let's
first count this, okay, the stuff that's directly outside the city. One,
two, three, four, five where
this was two thousand so it goes like that. Five, right? Five,
six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve, thirteen, fourteen, fifteen, sixteen.
Okay there's sixteen right? Yes? And there are sixteen if you add
the corners. Okay there you go. So there are thirty-two of those
units. So
משכחת לה במסכתא דהוה תרי אלפי על תרי אלפי. Mishkachat lah be-masechta
dahava try alphei al try alphei. תחום כמה הוה שיתסר. Tchum kamma
hava shitser. So how much is it? The two thousand extended out.
I mean an easy way to figure it out is just if
the city is two thousand and you extend out two thousand, two
by two is four, so you have four on each side, okay,
that's eight and sixteen, and then if you have four on each
side how much are the corners?
So קרנות כמה הוי שיתסר. Kronot kamma havei shitser. It's also because
the corners are defined by a four by four side, so it's
another sixteen. So you have thirty-two units there. How many of these
thirty-two units is the מגרש? migrash? So the מגרש migrash is one,
two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight of those and plus four
corners is twelve. So the מגרש migrash is twelve and the entire
all of this stuff outside is what did we say? Thirty-two. Okay
little problem still not a quarter. So let's see what we do.
Okay so תחום כמה הוה שיתסר קרנות כמה
הוי שיתסר. Tchum kamma hava shitser kronot kamma havei shitser. Okay let's
go let's
do it again. דהוה תרי אלפי על תרי אלפי. dahava try alphei
al try alphei.
תחום כמה הוה שיתסר. Tchum kamma hava shitser. קרנות כמה הוה
שיתסר. Kronot kamma hava shitser. דתמניא דתחומין De-tmanya de-tchumin eight for the
תחומין tchumin וארבעה דקרנות ve-arba de-kranot and four for the corners, meaning
this is the מגרש. migrash. כמה הוי תריסר Kamma havei treisar that's
twelve. נמצא מגרש רביע Nimtza migrash revia so the Gemara says נמצא
מגרש רביע nimtza migrash revia so I still don't get it, what
do you mean it's a quarter? טפי מתילתא הוי Tapei mi-tilsa havei
it's more than a third. Twelve out of thirty-two is more than
a third, it's not a quarter. So the Gemara says אה אייתי
ארבע דמתא שדי עלייהו. Ah aiti arba de-mata shadi aleihu. So when
we said it's a quarter we didn't mean it's a quarter of
the stuff outside of the city, we meant it's a quarter of
the entire, you know, of everything all together including the sides of
the city. So if the city is two thousand by two thousand,
how many thousand units does it have? Thousand by thousand it's four,
right? Okay, so the entirety is thirty-six. So now we still have
a problem though. Okay it's a third, it's not a quarter. Okay?
So the Gemara says אכתי תילתא הוי Akti tilsa havei it's still
a third. So the
Gemara says מי סברת בריבועא קאמרת? בעיגולא קאמרת. Mi savrat be-rivua kamart?
Be-igula kamart. What makes you think we're talking about a square city?
Talking about a circular city. Okay? וכמה מרובע יתר על העיגול רביע.
Ve-kamma meruba yeter al ha-igul revia. Now how much is a square
bigger than a circle? A quarter. Why?
Because if a circle is you know assuming pi is three, this
is true both for
circumference and for the and for the area. Okay? Because if this
is a radius of
well let's let's say the diameter is one, so this is but
no let's make it easier, let's say the diameter is two. Okay
this is two by two right? So it's a radius of one,
right? Okay so what so what's the area of the circle? Three
point... no the... okay the area of the square let's start with
that. Four. What is the area of
the
square? Pi. The area and what else
did I say? The circumference okay or perimeter whatever is... So, how
about the circle? So the area of the circle, that's the square.
How about the circle? Pi r squared, right? Pi r squared which
equals pi which equals because it's one equals three. Okay, so that
is the area. So it's three to four. How about the circumference?
The circumference is 2 pi r, right? 2 pi r which
is... so that's two, so it's 2 pi which is six. Okay,
so three to four, six to eight. So if pi is three,
the ratio... for us we could say the ratio is pi to
four, but for the Gemara גמרא Gemara the ratio is three to
four. Okay, of the area and the circumference. So, kama havei כמה
הוי. kama havei.
Okay, so it says, bribua k'mitkapla בריבועא כמתקפלא. b'ribu'a k'mitkapla. Kama meruba
yeter al igul? Revi'a כמה מרובע יתר על עיגול? רביע. Kama meruba
yeter al igul? Revi'a. So it's a quarter more, the square over
the circle. Dal revi'a minayhu דל רביע מינייהו, dal revi'a minaihu, take
a quarter out, pashlei lei tish'a פשלו ליה תשעה. pashlei lei tish'a.
That's nine. V'tish'a mitlatin v'shishta revi'a haveya ותשעה מתלתין ושיתא רביע הויא
v'tish'a mitlatin v'shishta revi'a haveya and nine out of thirty-six is a
quarter. Which means that the Gemara גמרא Gemara is assuming that the...
and that's actually a big chiddush חידוש... chiddush... is that the
migrash מגרש migrash is not squared off. Only the techum תחום techum
of the two thousand is squared off. But if you start with
a city that is in this case, right, two thousand, it's a
thousand radius, the migrash מגרש migrash is also a circle. Okay, not
a square. It's only the stuff outside that's squared off. So if
that's true, okay, and if we're saying that this is another thousand,
okay, then what is going to be the size of the migrash
מגרש? migrash? What's going to be the area of the circle? So
two thousand with a radius of two thousand, so what's the area
of the circle?
Pi r squared. Let's call it two, not two thousand, okay? So
it's
pi times four, which is twelve. Okay, that is the entire circle
including the middle. Yes, everybody with me more or less? So, and
the inner circle is how much? One thousand. So it's pi. Right?
The inner circle is pi, which is three. So
the migrash מגרש... migrash... the city is three and the migrash מגרש
migrash is nine. But the outer square hasn't changed, right? So the
outer square, the entire thing of everything is thirty-six because the outer
square is going to be the exact same and it's going to
give you all of this extra. So anyway, the nine is now
a quarter of everything. Alright, so that's how it works and that's
a big chiddush חידוש chiddush that you don't square off the city
or the migrash מגרש, migrash, you only square off the techum תחום.
techum. Alright, so that's what it says. Abaye amar אביי אמר: Abaye
amar: meshachachas lah nami b'mata d'hava alfa b'alfa משכחת לה נמי במתא
דהויא אלפא באלפא. meshachachas lah nami b'mata d'hava alfa b'alfa. It also
works with a city that is a thousand as opposed to two
thousand. Techumim kama havei? Temanya תחומין כמה הוו? תמניא. Techumim kama havei?
Temanya. The techumim תחומין techumim is eight. Karnas kama havei? Shisre קרנת
כמה הוו? שיסר. Karnas kama havei? Shisre. The corners are sixteen. Dal
arba'ah d'techumim v'arba'ah d'karnas דל ארבעה דתחומין וארבעה דקרנת. dal arba'ah d'techumim
v'arba'ah d'karnas. So you remove the eight for the migrash מגרש. migrash.
Kama havei? Temanya כמה הוו? תמניא. Kama havei? Temanya. It's eight. Tilsha
havei תילתא הוי, tilsha havei, which is a third. So that was
self-explanatory. Let me just do this... let's go to the whiteboard and
draw, and then we'll end with that. Because Abaye אביי Abaye said
if the city is a thousand, right, the city is a thousand,
right, not two thousand, it's a thousand. Okay, and then you have
a thousand here going around for the migrash מגרש migrash
and then another thousand for that, right? Yes? Okay. So what is
the... let's do this quickly. Okay, what is the size of the
migrash מגרש? migrash? So if this whole thing here is a thousand,
it's a square of three thousand by three thousand. People with me,
right? One, one, one for the migrash מגרש. migrash. So the entire
amount of the city plus the migrash מגרש migrash is nine million.
Okay, the city is a thousand by a thousand, so the city
is one and the migrash מגרש migrash is eight. Okay. Now, this
entire thing
though, that's two thousand. So four thousand by four thousand, everything is
how much? Four thousand... this is one, two, three, four, four thousand
by four thousand.
Am I doing that right? One, three, four, five...
wait.
One, three, four, five. It's five by five. Right, this is one,
this is two, and this is two, right? So it's five by
five. Yes? One, one, one...
No, no you don't add two thousand, you add one thousand past
the migrash מגרש. migrash.
I know. One plus one plus one. One plus one, two, three,
four, five. So everything is five by five is twenty-five.
It's six by six.
What did I do wrong?
It's the city's two. No, the city's one. Okay, you're right, you're
right.
It's...
How
do we get a third? How do we get a quarter?
One minute.
אביי אמר Abaye amar מגרש דמי migrash dami בבבא דהוה b'vava d'hava
אלפא באלפא. alpa b'alpa. תחומין כמה הוו Tchumin kama havay תמניא. tmanya.
So the תחום tchum is eight. קרנות כמה הוו Kranot kama havay
שיתסר, shitsar, twenty-four. Right, everything minus the city is twenty-four. That's right,
that's fine.
דל ארבע דתחומין Dal arba d'tchumin וארבע דקרנות v'arba d'kranot and the
מגרש migrash is four plus four, which is eight.
כמה הוו Kama havay תמניא? tmanya? תילתא הוי. Tilta havay. Oh, that's
what the גמרא Gemara says, so it's still not a quarter, תילתא
הוי, tilta havay, it's a third. So the גמרא Gemara says same
answer, מי סברת בריבוע קאמרת mi savrat b'ribuah ka'amart בעיגולא קאמר? b'igula
ka'amar? We're not talking about a square, we're talking about a circle.
So כמה מרובע יתר על העיגול רביע? kama meruba yeter al ha'igul
reviah? So again, if we're talking about a circle, so as opposed
to this
being nine, this as opposed to this being eight, this becomes six.
Right? And if it's six, six out of twenty-four is a quarter.
So כמה מרובע יתר על העיגול רביע, kama meruba yeter al ha'igul
reviah, דל רביע dal reviah פשו ליה שיתא. pashu lei shita. So
now it's six, ושיתא מכ"ד רביע הוי v'shita mi-kaf daled reviah havay
and therefore it's a quarter. יישר כח. Yasher koach. So the upshot
of all of this is that according to both answers, the city
and the מגרש migrash don't get squared off. Only when you get
to the final thousand do you square everything off, so the ratios
are larger than they otherwise would be. Okay, that was fun.